بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله  وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Lessons from the conversation between Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Rafea Bin Amr At-Taae(رافع بن عمروألطائ).
Number one, speak to the people according to their level.
حاطب الناس على قدر أقول
This is a thief, he didn't go to school, he has no education background.
Don't give him Bukhari(بخاريْ) and tell him memorize it
and don't tell him you have to go on a Shariah(شريعة) course for a few years and study ilm(علم).
People have different capabilities.
Not everybody will become a great Shaikh(شيخ) and scholar,
and not everybody will become an Imam(اِمَام), not everybody will be Daiyah(داعي)
Imagine if Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه recited to this man Surah Al-Baqarah(سورة ألبقرة) and told him to memorize it,
he could barely remember the five fingers, that's it.
So the gangsters and brothers from that background, teach them take it easy with them.
Take it easy with them.
And Alhamdulillah(ألحمدلله), some of these brothers turned out to be wonderful brothers,
when Allah guides them to the truth.
The spirit that they have, is sometimes a spirit that you cannot find with a scholar.
It happens that is Rizq(رزق) from Allah.
I mean, Imam Ahmad Bin Hanbal(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْبن حنبل) once he heard somebody speaking about Bishral Haafie(بشرالحافي).
He said: He's not a scholar.
Bishral Haafie(بشرالحافي) wasn't a scholar in terms of memorizing a lot of Hadith(حديث).
He's nothing to compare to Imam Ahmad Bin Hanbal(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْبن حنبل),
but what did Imam Ahmad Bin Hanbal(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْبن حنبل) say;
He already has the fruit of knowledge, Khashiat Allah(خشية الله).
He already has the fruit of knowledge which is the fear of Allah.
What does that Ayah(آية) say?
إِنَّمَا يَخْشَى اللَّهَ مِنْ عِبَادِهِ الْعُلَمَاءُ
The ones who have fear of Allah are the scholars.
So Allah is saying that the fruit of knowledge is the fear of Allah,
there is no benefit in knowledge that doesn’t make you fear Allah.
If you have all the knowledge in the world that you don't fear Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ it's worthless.
Ahmad Bin Hanbal(اَحْمَدْ بن حنبل) is saying this man already has the fruit of the knowledge.
Therefore, really in his situation, knowledge, it's important,
but he is a scholar in that sense, he has the fear of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ would speak to people differently.
And the Sahabah(صحابه) understood that.
Now Rasool Allah ﷺ when he is speaking to Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس), even though he was a child,
but because he had the mind of a scholar,
Rasool Allah ﷺ would speak to him on a very high level.
While a Bedouin would come to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and he would give him very brief orders that are easy to remember.
So, you have to have Hikmah(حكمة) in Da'wah(دعوة)
speak to the people according to their abilities.
Number two, be honest,
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه did not hold back anything.
He said: Don't be a leader.
And this is the first conversation he is having with the man he doesn't even know him well,
don't be a leader.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) for some reason or another saw some things in this man,
that do not befit position of authority.
So he was very honest with him, told him don't be a leader.
So also when you see something wrong in your brother, correct them.
It's fine, it's okay, do it in a very nice way.
FATTEH MAKKAH(فتح مكه), THE OPENING OF MAKKAH,
Rasool Allah ﷺ had an agreement with the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), a truce,
no war, that was in Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبية).
One  term in the agreement stated that if anyone wanted to enter into a coalition with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
they have the right to do so.
And if anyone wanted to enter into coalition with Muhammadﷺ they have the right to do so.
So according to the agreement, both sides are free to make alliances.
Bannu Bakr(بنوبكر) entered into an alliance with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
Khuza'a(خزاعه) entered into an alliance with Muhammadﷺ.
Khuza'a(خزاعه) had a special relationship with the grandfather of Muhammadﷺ
and they carried on with the relationship with Muhammadﷺ,
even though they were Mushrikeen(مشركين), but they wanted to be on his side.
They had an alliance with his grandfather and they wanted to continue the alliance of Muhammadﷺ,
even though they were Mushrikeen(مشركين).
There was a feud between Bannu Bakr(بنوبكر) and Khuza'a(خزاعه),
they were at each other's necks.
Bannu Bakr(بنوبكر), made an agreement, a secret agreement with some men in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
that they provide them with weapons,
and they make an ambush on Khuza'a(خزاعه) at night kill them and disappear.
So some men of Khuza'a(خزاعه) were killed.
Amr Bin Salim(عمروبن سالم), came to Muhammadﷺ,
and he narrated lines of poetry, asking Muhammadﷺ to fulfill the agreement, and give him victory,
that we have been betrayed by Bannu Bakr(بنوبكر) and we've been betrayed by Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ immediately said:
نُصرت يا عمرو بن سالم
I will give you victory.
Rasool Allah ﷺ went back home and he told Ayesha رضي الله عنها to prepare his luggage for battle,
food and everything that he needed for this journey,
but Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to make this expedition secret.
Why? Because he wanted to avoid bloodshed in Makkah.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to mobilize his army and attack Makkah suddenly
so that the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), only realized when it's too late for them to fight back,
so that he can protect their blood.
He doesn't want to give them time to prepare for war.
So he wants to make his move, clandestine and quiet.
So he told Ayesha(عائشه) to prepare everything for him.
So she was grinding, some grain.
Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه, he came into the house and he saw that she was preparing luggage and all that,
he said:
لعلى رسول الله يُريدو غزوة
Is Rasool Allah ﷺ thinking about attacking an enemy?
She didn't respond.
He told her, does he intend to fight the Romans?
Does he intend to fight the people of Najd(نجد)?
She didn't respond.
Does he intend to fight the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)?
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ came in.
So he asked him: O Messenger of Allah, are you planning for war?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes.
He said: Is it with the Romans?
Rasool Ullah said: No!
Is it with the people of Najd(نجد).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: No.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: Then is it the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes!
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) responded don't we have a truce between us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Didn't you hear what they did to Bannu Ka'ab(بنوكعب).?
They have breached the agreement.
Now, look at the conduct of Ayesha رضي الله عنها she kept quiet.
To protect the secret of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Even with her father the closest man to Muhammadﷺ.
Muhammadﷺ didn't keep his secret from Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he told him,
but Ayesha(عائشه) kept quite.
The Battle of Hunain(حنين).
Abu Qatadah Al-Ansari(أبوقتادةألأنصاري) from Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار). He said;
I saw a Muslim, fighting with a Mushrik(مشرك).
And there was another Mushrik(مشرك), who was trying to get around the Muslim and attack him from behind.
So I attacked that Mushrik(مشرك) to protect my brother,
when he saw me he lifted up his arm to hit me with his sword,
but I was faster so I chopped off his arm.
But then he hugged me, and he terrified me with his hug and then he became weaker.
So I was able to kill him.
But then we retreated so I had to leave.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
من قتل قتيلًا فله’ سلبه’
If you killed anyone, then you can take their Salb(سلب),
Salb(سلب) is whatever is with the fighter, there's a Ghanimah(غنيمه) and there is Salb(سلب).
Ghanimah(غنيمه) is the booty of war, that’s all of the heavy equipments,
the camels, the horses, the wealth of the people that is booty.
There is a different Hukum(حكم) for booty than there is for Salb(سلب).
For booty the Ameer(أمير) divides it four fifths, goes to the fighters,
and 1/5 is divided into five sections, that’s in the Ahkaam(أحكام) of Ghanaem(غنائم).
But with As-Salb(ألسَّلب) it all goes to the fighter.
So the personal weapons that are found on a dead soldier are taken by the one, who killed them.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said whoever killed someone, you take their Salb(سلب), you take their weapons.
And there's a difference of opinion on what exactly is included in Salb(سلب).
If you find some cash with them, their clothes,
but that's something to look into in the books of Fiqh(فقه).
Abu Qatadah(أبوقتادة) went and he found that there's nothing on this man, it was all taken
and weapons are very expensive, and Abu Qatadah(أبوقتادة) was very poor.
He went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and there were some people with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he said: O Messenger of Allah, I have killed this man, and I can't find his weapons.
So one of the Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), who were there, he said: I am the one, who took the Salb(سلب),
I am the one, who took the weapons.
So O Messenger of Allah, ask him to allow me to keep it.
And that was the man whom Abu Qatadah(أبوقتادة) defended.
Before Rasool Allah ﷺ responds, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) intervened and he said: No,
In the Name of Allah, a weak bird from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
is not going to take away the Salb(سلب) of a lion, of the lions of Allah,
who's defending Allah and His Messenger.
Now, the man who took the Salb(سلب) is from the Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), the people of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
and Abu Qatadah(أبوقتادة) is from Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار),
but Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) here is interfering and saying: The weak bird from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
meaning you are the weak one, and he came to defend you,
the weak bird of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) is not going to keep the weapons,
but it should go to the lion of Allah, who is fighting to defend Allah and His Messenger.
Rasool Allah ﷺ approved the Fatwa(فتوى) of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
and he told the man, give him, his weapons back.
The point to illustrate from the story is that
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)was at a level where he can give Fatwa(فتوى) in the presence of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
where he can make a judgment in the court of Muhammadﷺ,
he can make a ruling, when Rasool Allah ﷺ is right there.
That is how intimate and close the relationship was because Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
was drinking from the fountain of Prophethood for years and years,
he has the Hikmah(حكمة) and wisdom, and Rasool Allah ﷺ approves, his ruling.
Another thing worthy of mentioned in the Battle of Hunain(حنين),
there were a lot of Ghanaem(غنائم), booties of war, alot,
and there were many new Muslims in the army.
Rasool Allah ﷺ gave these new Muslims the booty of war.
And he withheld it from Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) and the old Muslims.
In order to draw these new Muslims closer to Islam,
but still there was greed among these, some of these new converts.
Al-Abbas Bin Mardaas(ألعباس بن مرداس), he was one of the chiefs of a clan, he made long poetry,
because he was upset, how come Rasool Allah ﷺ gives him equal to or less than Al-Aqra'a(ألأقراء) or Oyeyna(عيينة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ gave them a certain amount,
and Al-Abbas Bin Mardaas(ألعباس بن مرداس) didn't like that because he saw it as a matter of status.
Whoever, is lowered on this day cannot be raised.
You have lowered my status, and the Arabs will see that, that is my status and I cannot go up,
so you have to give me equal to them.
And there was a line of poetry. He says:
جعلت نهبي ونهب العبيد، بين عيينه وأقراع
When Rasool Allah ﷺ heard this poetry. He said: Go and cut his tongue.
Not literally.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ meant is give him, until he is quiet,
cut his tongue means make him happy, so that his tongue wouldn't say something like that.
Because poetry was powerful.
I mean, when we say that Ka'ab Ibn Ashraf(كعب إبن أشرف) was making poetry against the women of the Sahabah(صحابه),
poetry in Arabia had a greater influence on people, then a blockbuster movie would have today,
or a front page article on The New York Times, or primetime TV with the BBC.
I mean poetry in with the Arabs was a very big deal, it was the media of the day.
And there's an instance where one line of poetry,
brought the end to the reputation of a tribe.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Go and cut his tongue,
so they gave him and they gave him camels until he was happy.
Later on, Rasool Allah ﷺ met with Al-Abbas(العباس), he met him,
And he said: Are you the one, who said:
جعلت نهبي ونهب العبيد، بين أقراع و عيينه
In the line of poetry, it is Uyeyna(عيينه) and then Al-Aqrah(ألأقراع).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ narrated that line of poetry. He said,
he switched the names.
He said: Al-Aqrah(ألأقراع) and Uyeyna(عيينه).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) corrected Rasool Allah ﷺ and he said: No! It's not
Al-Aqrah(ألأقراع) and Uyeyna(عيينه), it is Uyeyna(عيينه) and Al-Aqrah(ألأقراع).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: It's the same thing.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) smiled and said:
You are truly as Allah said:
وَمَا عَلَّمْنَاهُ الشِّعْرَ وَمَا يَنبَغِي لَهُ ۚ إِنْ هُوَ إِلَّا ذِكْرٌ وَقُرْآنٌ مُّبِينٌ۝
We have not taught him poetry and it's not appropriate for him.
It is only remembrance of Allah, and a manifest Book.
I mean Rasool Allah ﷺ made this mistake in the poetry, it doesn't change the meaning,
it's just the sequence of the names.
So when Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) corrected it, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: It doesn't make a difference.
To Rasool Allah ﷺ, it doesn't make a difference,
but to the listeners of poetry, you have to follow the rules.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said: Yes! You're as Allah said:
وَمَا عَلَّمْنَاهُ الشِّعْرَ
We did not teach him poetry, and it's not appropriate for him, but it is Qur'an.
In the siege of At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف) when the Muslims were laying siege to At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف),
an arrow injured the son of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, Abdullah(عبدالله)
and that injury was the cause of his death, but it was a long time after that it happened,
he only died after Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away.
When Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was Khalifah(خليفه).
He received the delegation from At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف).
This was a long time after the incident happened of shooting the arrow,
shooting the arrow happened in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
his son died because of it, during the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) retained the arrow, he kept it with him.
It was the cause of the death of his son, Abdullah(عبدالله).
When he received the delegation from At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف), coming to visit him as the Khalifah(خليفه),
he pulled out the arrow, and he said: Is any one of you know the source of this arrow.
It happened that one of the men who were present,
he said: I am the one who prepared this arrow, I'm the one who sharpened it,
I'm the one, who attach the feathers to it, and I'm the one who shot it.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: This is the arrow that killed my son Abdullah(عبدالله).
What was the response of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he lost his son.
He said: So Praised be to Allah, who honored him, through you.
And did not dishonor you and made you a Muslim
and that is better for both of you.
Allah honored my sons, through you, you are the one, who made him a Shaheed(شهيد).
And Allah did not dishonor you, He made you a Muslim so it's good for you.
And there's a narration that says, the two men, who love each other the most in Jannah(جنة),
are the Kafir(كافر) who killed the Muslim, and then became a Muslim himself.
They end up loving each other so much in Jannah(جنة).
Because the martyr knows that this is the one, who killed me and gave me this status.
And that person praised Allah that he did not, wasn't punished for that
and he ended up becoming a muslim himself, so that's At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف).
Tabook(تبوك),
The Battle of Tabook(تبوك), was the first time Rasool Allah ﷺ by himself will go out and face the Romans,
there was an initial encounter in the Battle of Mu'tah(مؤته),
but this time Rasool Allah ﷺ wants to go, himself, and lead an army
and make an incursion into the Roman Empire.
So it was a very special event, it needed some special preparation,
different than any other battle that Rasool Allah ﷺ participated in.
And in this battle, he gave the great banner to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
When the army marched out, and there were camping at night.
This was a long journey so one of those nights they were out in the desert camping.
So Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) said: I saw a fire in the distance,
so I wanted to go and see what was happening.
He said: I went there and I found, Abdullah Ibn Abi Bajadain(عبدالله إبن أبي بجادين) dead.
This is one of the companions of Rasool Ullah,
and with him were Rasool Allah ﷺ, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ was in the grave.
And he was telling, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر) to lower the body of Abdullah(عبدالله).
He said: Bring down your brother,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ placed him with his own hands in the grave, and then he said:
اللهم إني أمسيت عليه راضيً فرداعني
O Allah! I am going to bed this night and I'm pleased with him
so O, Allah be pleased with him.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) said: I desire and wished that I was the one in that grave.
To receive this Dua(دُعَا) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
that I am pleased with him, so O Allah be pleased with him.
Again it was Rasool Allah ﷺ Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر).
It was very difficult time, hot in summer.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: It got to a level where we didn't have any water left,
so we would slaughter our camels and drink whatever is in their stomachs
the digested food, they will drink that that's how thirsty they were.
And then he said, and we take whatever is left and
we put we will put it on our bodies to cool down.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه when to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said:
O Messenger of Allah, your Dua(دُعَا) is accepted, make Dua(دُعَا) for us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ asked Abu Bakr(أبوبكر)
أوَ تحب ذالك؟
Is that something you want, you love that?
Meaning I will do it for you.
Is that what you want?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said: Yes!
Rasool Allah ﷺ made Dua(دُعَا), the narrative of the Hadith(حديث) says:
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not bring his hands down, until the clouds are above our heads.
In the spending in the Battle of the Tabook(تبوك)
and the spending in the Battle of Tabook(تبوك) was special.
That is when Rasool Allah ﷺ praised Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان)
and we talked about that in our first session.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was asking for donations for the preparation of the Army.
صادف ذالك عندي مالي
At that time, I had some money.
So I told myself today I am going to be ahead of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
if I'm ever going to be ahead of him, this is my chance.
So he said: I carried with me half of my wealth
and I went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and I gave it to him.
He said: O Umar(عُمَر)! What have you left for your family?
He said: I left them, half of my wealth.
And then Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) came
and he gave his money to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ asked him: What have you left for your family.
He said: I've left them Allah and His Messenger.
He brought all of his wealth!
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I will never try again to compete with you.
I'm never going to try to be ahead of you, He can't!
And this is in Tabook(تبوك).
So Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) persisted in his attempts all the way until the Battle of Tabook(تبوك)
but then he said: I am not gonna do it again Khalas(خلاص), I give up.
AL-HAJJ(حَجْ),
In Ninth year of Hijrah(هجرة), which is Hajja Tul Widdah(حجةالوداع)
Before Hajja Tul Widdah(حجةالوداع) the year before Hajja Tul Widdah(حجةالوداع)
Rasool Allah ﷺ appointed Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to lead the Hajj(حَجْ).
He appointed Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to lead the Hajj(حَجْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to make Hajj(حَجْ) himself, but he said:
It's not appropriate for me to make Hajj(حَجْ)
when there are people who are going around Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) naked.
There was a belief among the Arabs that only the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are pure
therefore they can make Tawaf(طواف) with their clothes.
But because we commit sins, our clothes are impure so we have to take them off
and they would make Tawaf(طواف) naked.
Now, not every one of them would do that.
They used to believe that if they want to make Tawaf(طواف) around Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
they have to borrow the clothes or buy the clothes of somebody from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Because they are the pure people.
So if they would have money they would buy clothes, whoever doesn't have money, they would make Tawaf(طواف) naked.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said: It's not appropriate for me to make Tawaf(طواف) when this is going on.
So he told Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه to lead, Al-Hajj(ألحَجْ).
And this is an indication that sometimes a leader needs to stay away from things
that are allowed for the rest of the Ummah(امة).
Because of that important position of leadership.
Rasool Allah ﷺ didn't do it himself, but he allowed the Muslims to go and make Hajj(حَجْ).
So the leader needs to follow stricter rules than the layman, to uphold a higher standard.
Anyway, Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) left.
When he left, Rasool Allah ﷺ received the revelation.
The first Ayaat(آيات) from Surah At-Taubah(سورة ألتوبة)
which are announcing the end of the agreement between Rasool Allah ﷺ and Kuffar(كفار)
and the end of the era of Shirk(شرك) in Arabia, it's over.
Now, it's either Islam or the sword, no other choice.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ told Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) to take his camel Al-Adba'a(ألعضباء), and to go fast,
and follow Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
and to convey to the people, to recite the Ayaat(آيات) of Surah Al-Bara'a(سورة ألبراء) to the people.
And it's the only Surah(سورة) in Qur'an that doesn’t start with,
بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم
Because it's an announcement of war
so it doesn't start with the Merciful and the Beneficent.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) went very fast, until he reached Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه in Dhul Khalifah(ذوالخليفه).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه saw him riding the camel of Rasool Allah ﷺ, he told him:
أميرٌ أمَّعمور
Are you leading or are you a follower.?
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said:
بل معمور
I'm a follower
because Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) thought that maybe Ali(علي) is a new leader of Al-Hajj(حَجْ).
He said: No! I am a follower.
So they went to Makkah
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) would take the people in the different positions of Hajj(حَجْ) in the different rituals,
and Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) would follow him wherever he goes,
and would recite the Ayaat(آيات) of Bara'a(برآء) on everyone
and then he would announce four things.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him to tell the people the following:
Number one;
لا يدخل الّجنة إلَّا مؤمن
No one will enter Jannah(جنة), unless they're believers.
Number two
ولا يطوفو بالبيت عريان
No one should make the Tawaf(طواف) around Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) - if they're naked.
Number three,
ومن كان بينه و بين رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عهدُ وعهدٌ على مدة
And if you have a peace agreement between you and Muhammadﷺ
then it ends at the end of the term, and it won't be renewed.
And finally
ولا يحج بعد العام مشرك
And no Mushrik(مشرك) shall make Hajj(حَجْ) after this year.
So, the era of Shirk(شرك) is over with, Shirk(شرك) is now behind our backs.
So Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) made these terms clear
as a preparation for Rasool Allah ﷺ coming the next year and leading the Hajj(حَجْ)
with no Shirk(شرك) around.
So, Makkah will now be purified.
Now notice the clear instructions
لا يدخل الّجنة إلَّا مؤمن
That only the believers will enter into Jannah(جنة).
Numbers two;
ولا يطوفو بالبيت عريان
No more nakedness around Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), to purify Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
and then the truce agreements.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not breach any agreement he said: You have four months
and after that, all agreements are terminated, and it's either Islam or the sword.
So this is in Hajjat(حجة) Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
In Hajjal Waddah(حج الوداع) and this is the only Hajj(حَجْ), that Rasool Allah ﷺ did
Hajjat-Tul-Widaa(حجة الوداع), the only thing that I would mention here is an incident.
Asma(أسماء) is narrating this she said:
Rasool Allah ﷺ was sitting with Ayesha(عائشه) sitting next to him and
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is waiting for his servant to bring back his camel
and is waiting and waiting and the servant was late
and then suddenly here comes the servant, without the camel.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) told him: Where's the camel, he said I lost it yesterday
What?
He attacked him and he started beating him.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ smiled and he said: Look at what this Muhram(مُحرم) man is doing
he is in the State of Ehraam(إحرام).
But that was the only camel that Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) had
so he was very upset that his servants lost his camel.
So, this is the end of the Jihad(جهاد) of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
We'll move on to the next stage.
In sha Allah Ho Ta'ala(إن شاء الله تعالى) this session we'll go through some events
involving Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه in Madina.
We talked in the previous session about the participation of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه in the Ghazawaat(غزوات).
So now we'll talk about the non Ghazawaat(غزوات)
events that happened with As-Siddique رضوان الله عليه.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would protect the secret of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
The daughter of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه, Hafsa(حفصه)
was married to one of the Sahabah(صحابه), who has fought in the Battle of Badr(بدر) later on, he died.
So Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه wanted his daughter to marry from the best.
So he went to Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) and he offered his daughter to him.
He told Uthman Ibn Affan رضي الله عنه do you want to marry my daughter Hafsa(حفصه)?
Uthman Ibn Affan رضي الله عنه said: Let me think about it.
He later on came back and said;
قد بدالي ألَّا تزوجه يوم هذا
I've decided that I don't want to marry at this particular time
I'm not interested in marriage now.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه might have disliked that a little bit
so he went to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
And he told him I'm offering you my daughter, if you want to marry her.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه did not respond, didn't say anything.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I was even more upset with Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) than I was with Uthman(عثمان).
At least Uthman(عثمان) came and gave me an answer
even though it was a no answer, but at least he gave me an answer.
But Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was silent
I offer my daughter to him, he doesn't give me an answer.
A few days later, Rasool Allah ﷺ, marries Hafsa(حفصه).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه after the marriage he came to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
and said: I think that you were upset with me because I didn't give you an answer
He said: Yes! I was upset with you.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
The reason why I didn't respond back is, because I heard Rasool Allah ﷺ mention her
and I wasn't going to be the one who would disclose the secret of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and if he did not marry her, I would have married her.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: I felt that Rasool Allah ﷺ by mentioning her name was interested in her.
And that's why I kept quiet to wait and see what will happen?
If Rasool Allah ﷺ does not marry her, I would have married her.
But I am not going to be the one, who will disclose the secret of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Ullah صلوات الله ولسلام عليه , wanted to have a relationship, a marriage relationship
with the fourth Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
So you find that he married the daughter of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
and he married the daughter of Umar Al-Farooq(عُمَرألفاروق)
and then he married two of his daughters to Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان)
first he married him one and then when she passed away he married him the other.
And there is a statement that says;
Allah Ho Alam(الله أعلم) how strong the narration is but
if I had 99 daughters, I would marry them to Uthman(عثمان)
if one of them die, I will keep on marrying him.
That is how much love Rasool Allah ﷺ had for Uthman Ibn Affan رضي الله عنه
and then he married his daughter, Fatima(فاطمه) to Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب).
So now, Rasool Allah ﷺ has a relationship, family relationship
with the four Khulafa'a رضي الله عنهم.
Two things here to note, number one marriage in those days was very easy, very easy.
Now we have complicated marriage so much
we have placed so much bureaucracy in marriage.
That unfortunately Haram(حرام) became easier than Halal(حلال).
In the time of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, things were very simple.
First of all, the nature of the Sahabah(صحابه), as Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) says:
كانو أقَّلِّ النَاس تكلفا
They were the least superficial among people, they hated complications
and they lived a very simple life, and they loved simplicity.
They were the furthest from complication or sophistication.
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم were simple in their dress, simple in their food
simple in their furniture, simpler in their houses, simple in everything.
And they cherished and they loved that simplicity, it is not like, that's all what they knew
No! Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) says:
I have knowledge about all of these fancy dishes and food.
But this is how I want to live, I want to live simplicity, it's not due to ignorance.
They viewed that as a better way.
So marriage was very simple.
And you can notice that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه is offering his daughter, who would do that today.
Who would go to somebody whom they know is a good person, a righteous person
a brother who is in need of marriage, and then tell them.
I would offer you my daughter who would do that now?
They just think that it's just shame, it's embarrassing, it's not good,
it's lower in your status, but Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) didn't have a problem with that
he went and he offered his daughter to Uthman(عثمان)
he offered her to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
because he wants the best for his daughter.
And in those days because marriage was so simple and easy.
There wasn't anything called an unmarried woman
which is called an Arabic Unoosa(عنوسه), woman who are unmarried
who're deprived from the blessing of marriage.
In those days there was a rule that you take care of every woman in the society
every woman would be taken care of.
So one of the purposes of polygamy was, so that the whole society is taken care of.
Nobody is left out of this important relationship.
Because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has created us in pairs, Azwaaja(أزواج).
And it's part of the nature of the man and a woman to be in such a relationship.
So therefore no one in the society would be left out and deprived of this
and Rasool Allah ﷺ told the ones, who wanted to choose a different path
that this is not my Sunnah(سنة).
The ones, who wanted to practice a life of celibacy and get away from marriage
because they heard that this was the practice of the Christian monks
Rasool Allah ﷺ said this is not my Sunnah(سنة), this is not my way,
my way is the way of marriage and whoever doesn't follow my way, doesn't belong to me.
So marriage in Islam is Ibadah(عبادة), it's form of worship
and we please Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ through it.
So, I would like to urge all the parents to make marriage easy,
so that they can keep their boys and girls away from Haram(حرام).
In the time of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم Halaal(حلال) was easier than Haram(حرام)
Haram(حرام) was very difficult to commit Haram(حرام) was very difficult.
But the path of Halaal(حلال) was very easy.
However, now things, especially in Western societies
every Haram(حرام) is available and it's not only available it's promoted.
Because we are living in times when good is evil and evil is good.
So this is something that the Muslim families need to break these rigid traditions that don't belong to Islam.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) as a scholar say every Bid'ah(بدعة) replaces a Sunnah(سنة)
everything wrong is only there because it has uprooted something that was right.
Therefore we should go back to the way of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم in making things simple and encouraging Halaal(حلال),
and Rasool Allah ﷺ says:
من استطاع منكم باه في اليتزوج
Marriage should be done in an early age.
We ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to make it easy on our brothers and sisters, who are seeking marriage
to make Halal(حلال) an open door for them
and to close the doors of Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) in their faces.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was giving Khutba Al-Jumu'ah(خطبة الجمعه).
When the caravan came in to Madina.
They used to sent out caravans to go to Ash-sham(ألشام) and to Yemen to bring back merchandise.
So these caravans would come back a few times a year, and the caravan would be led by a group of men
and it includes the money of the whole community.
So everybody would invest in that caravan, to go out and they would all wait for it
in anticipation, eager for its return that was their livelihood.
So it was a very, very big event when the caravan arrives
and everybody jumps in there to get the best deal.
It happened that the caravan arrived when Rasool Allah ﷺ was giving Khutba Al-Jumu'ah(خطبة الجمعه).
And the rules of Jumu'ah(جمعه) are still not clear in terms of you're not supposed to move
and you're not supposed to speak
so everyone left the Masjid(مسجد)
and only a few remained with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
It wasn't mandatory yet for them to remain, at least that's how we would assume
we wouldn't imagine that the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم would leave when they have an understanding that it's mandatory.
So it must have been before the final rules of Jumu'ah(جمعه) were given, so they left.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ revealed the Ayah(آية) in Surat-Ul-Jumu'ah(سورة الجمعه).
وَإِذَا رَأَوْا تِجَارَةً أَوْ لَهْوًا انفَضُّوا إِلَيْهَا وَتَرَكُوكَ قَائِمًا
قُلْ مَا عِندَ اللَّهِ خَيْرٌ مِّنَ اللَّهْوِ وَمِنَ التِّجَارَةِ ۚ وَاللَّهُ خَيْرُ الرَّازِقِينَ۝
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says, but when they saw a transaction or diversion
O Muhammad(محمد), they rushed to it, and left you standing
say what is with Allah is better than diversion, and then a transaction
and Allah is the best of providers.
They left, and you were standing in the Masjid(مسجد)
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is saying that what Allah has is better than this business
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is the One, Who gives Rizq(رزق).
You left Salaat-Ul-Jumu'ah(جمعه), to go and meet the caravan
while Rasool Allah ﷺ was giving Kht'bah(خطبه).
Now it says, in the narration of this statement that only 12 remained
and among those 12 were Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar رضي الله عنهما.
So you would find them always on the right side
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar رضي الله عنهما even though both of them were businessmen
and they had a lot of interest to go and meet the caravan, but they stayed behind
until Rasool Allah ﷺ finishes his Khut'bah(خطبة).
So they were not included among the ones in this Ayah(آية).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says, in a Hadith(حديث) in Bukhari(بخاريْ)
من جرَّا ثوبه’ خيالآء لم ننظر الله عليه يوم القيامة
If your Izaar(إزار) is dragging, under the ankle out of pride and showing off,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will not look at you, on the Day of Judgment.
So the Sunnah(وکع) is to wear the clothes, above the ankle.
Now, Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق), as I mentioned was very slim.
So when he would tie his Izaar(إزار) around his waist, because of his thinness
his Izaar(إزار) would slip, he was very slim so it wouldn't hold on his waist.
So he told Rasool Allah ﷺ, O Messenger of Allah,
My Izaar(إزار) wouldn't hold to my waist and it would slip down and go under the ankle
and the only way for me to keep it above the ankle is to continue all the time tugging it up.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him that you are not among the ones
who are doing it out of pride, out of arrogance.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: You are not included in this Hadith(حديث).
So this is a Shahadah(شهادة) from Rasool Allah ﷺ
that Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is free from arrogance, and we know how great of a sin arrogance is.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: Whoever has a single grain of arrogance in their hearts will not even smell paradise.
So we ask Allah سبحانه وتعالى to keep us away from this evil sin
which has brought the demise of Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ), Iblees(إبليس).
That's how Iblees(إبليس) lost his very high status among the angels.
It is because of arrogance.
أنا خير منه
I'm better than him!
Why should I make Sujood(سجود) for him, while, I'm better than him?
And that's why they say that the worst thing for Iblees(إبليس) is to see you making Sujood(سجود)
because his refusal of Sujood(سجود) is what brought the wrath of Allah on him.
And when he sees the Muslim making Sujood(سجود)
he knows that this is what will bring the Mercy of Allah on that person
so he hates, he dislikes Sujood(سجود).
You anger Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) when you make Sujood(سجود) to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Because Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) says:
أمرت بسجود فلم أسجد وامر إبن آدم بالسجود فسجد
I was ordered to make Sujood(سجود) and I refused
and the son of Adam(آدم) was ordered to make Sujood(سجود) and he did.
Number four:
During Eid(عيد) Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه went to visit his daughter Ayesha(عائشه).
He comes in and he finds two young girls from the Ansaar(أنْصَار) singing for her
special performance for Ayesha رضي الله عنها.
No instruments were used in this according to this particular narration, they were singing.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, when he saw that he was very angry and he said:
أبى مضموع الشيطان في بيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
You're using the flute of the devil in the house of Rasool Allah ﷺ
singing in the house of Muhammad صلوات الله والسلام عليه
he was very upset with his daughter.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ was there and Rasool Allah ﷺ was facing the wall
so he didn't see Ayesha(عائشه) and he didn’t see Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
but he spoke to them without looking back. He said;
يا أبا بكر إنَّا لكل قومٍ عيدا وهذ عيدنا
And this is in Muslim(ألمسلم).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
O Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), every people have a celebration.
And this is our celebration, Eid, a day of celebration.
Rasool Allah ﷺ approved what Ayesha(عائشه) was doing
and Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
that in situations like these, it is appropriate and fine to celebrate
and Rasool Allah ﷺ says in another Hadith(حديث).
ليعمل المشركون أنَّ في ديننا فصحا
We want the Mushrikeen(مشركين), the disbelievers to know
that there is room for entertainment in our religion.
There is room for one to entertain themselves as long as it's done in a Halal(حلال) fashion.
So, as a human being there is a compartment, in your compartments of needs of entertainment
your soul and your heart and your body needs this.
It is different according to people
some people their compartment of entertainment is larger than others but everybody has a need.
Obviously in Islam, we're encouraged to be serious
because this is a serious religion.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says:
يَا يَحْيَىٰ خُذِ الْكِتَابَ بِقُوَّةٍ ۖ
Oh Yahya(يحي), hold the book with strength and power
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says to Banni Israel(بني اسرائيل):
خُذُوا مَا آتَيْنَاكُمْ بِقُوَّةٍ
Take what We have given you, the commands We have given you with strength.
So the religion is serious, but then there is on the side, time for one to entertain their souls.
But we shouldn't turn the whole religion into entertainment and fun
because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says about the disbelievers.
اتَّخَذُوا دِينَهُمْ لَعِبًا وَلَهْوًا
They have taken the religion to be an entertainment and fun
And in the Masjid(مسجد) I used to be the Imam(اِمَام) in the U.S.
We used to have some church groups, visit us, and they would come and see the Salah(صلاة)
they would be impressed with the Salah(صلاة), they would like it they would see the Khut'ba(خطبه)
they would see the Ibadah(عبادة) of the Muslims in Masjid(مسجد)
but quite often, they would ask the question, you don't have any singing in your Mosques.?
You don't have any group to sing and perform for you in the mosque?
We would say: No! This is our Ibadah(عبادة) this is how it is.
They would view it as very bland and plain.
That is because they got used to singing and entertainment in the church
and I had a professor in social sciences, who was an atheist.
He didn't believe in God, but he said: I still like to go to the church,
because I love the songs.
But Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) even though there's no singing in the Masjid(مسجد)
and there's no entertainment in the sense of the modern definition of entertainment
but Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ puts a certain Sakinah(سكينه) in the heart because being in the masjid(مسجد).
When you hear the Qur'an, the lining up in the Salah(صلاة)
the movement in cohesion with everybody else.
The whole sight of Salah(صلاة) is impressive
and when you see the sight of 2 million people in Salah At-Taraweeh(ألصلاة التراويح) in Al-Haram(ألحرم),
making Sujood(سجود) together, making Rukooh(ركوع) together
listening to the recitation of Qur'an, it's a very powerful scene.
When you look at Hajj(حَجْ), there's no singing going on, in Hajj(حَجْ)
but it's a powerful image.
So Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), a Muslim who experiences this.
just think about - how the deprived the person is,
if they don't have Salah(صلاة) in their lives.
Could you imagine living without making Sujood(سجود)
can you imagine living without Salaat-Ul-Jama'ah(صلاةالجماعة)
can you imagine living without having the concept of Ramadan(رمضان)
no fasting, no Taraweeh(تراويح), no breaking your fast, that happiness and pleasure
that comes with eating the first dates, when you're hungry.
Can you imagine how deprive the person would be
when they don't have the concept of Hajj(حَجْ), they don't know what Hajj(حَجْ) is
they never seen it, they never experienced it
without having the celebration of Eid(عيد).
So even though there's no singing, and entertainment in Islam, but it is so fulfilling.
It makes your life, full, with joy and happiness.
Ibn Taymiyyah(إبن تيمية) when they, put him in jail
and then they threatened him to do this and that. He said:
What can my enemy do with me.? My Jannah(جنة) is in my heart
my Paradise is in my heart.
If they put me in jail I will use that time to make Zikr(زكر) of Allah.
And if they kill me, I am a Shaheed(شهيد).
So what can they do.
So the Mo'min(مؤمن) is carrying the Jannah(جنة)
the pleasure, the tranquility with them in their hearts.
For those of you, who have experienced in Masjid-Al-Nabwi(مسجد ألنبوي).
I mean, imagine how the deprived the person is, if they never have a chance
to sit inside Ar-Raodha(ألروضه), which is part of Jannah(جنة).
So Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has blessed us and we shouldn't take this for granted and we should say;
ألحمدلله رب العلمين
We don't have any musical instruments going on in the Masjid(مسجد)
but it's more fulfilling than the best musical concert in the world.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has blessed us and we should say Alhamdolillah(ألحمدلله).
But again, we have to fulfill that deep need inside for entertainment.
And that's why, for example, that's one of the purposes of marriage.
وَجَعَلَ بَيْنَكُم مَّوَدَّةً وَرَحْمَةً ۚ
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has made between the man and woman, mercy, and compassion
and there are many forms of entertainment that serve a dual purpose.
Like sports, not only is this a form of entertainment for you but it's also preparation.
So we ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to give us the correct understanding in His religion
because both extremes are very dangerous.
We also noticed that this wasn't the habit
Otherwise Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would not say what he said.
So it wasn't the habit that they always have singing going on
it was a once in a while thing.
And according to the majority of the scholars all instruments are not allowed, with the exception of the tambourine.
This situation Ayesha رضي الله عنها  had two young girls from an Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار), singing for her.
The generosity of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
In Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(ألمسلم), you know about Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه)
they were named Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه) these were the poor Sahabah(صحابه), mostly Muhajireen(مهاجرين)
from Makkah or from other places, who didn't have houses in Madina.
So they ended up staying in a corner, in the Masjid(مسجد).
They are very poor, they couldn't afford buying a house
so Rasool Allah ﷺ allowed them to stay in a certain corner in the Masjid(مسجد)
those were their living quarters in the Masjid(مسجد) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and it wasn't only the poor
but sometimes also the young among the Sahabah(صحابه) would go and join them.
So Abdullah Ibn Umar رضي الله عنه said;
I spent two years in Masjid(مسجد) before I got married.
He would stay in Masjid(مسجد) full time in order to be close to Rasool Allah ﷺ
because that's where Rasool Allah ﷺ would conduct his lesson.
He said:
وانا اللعازب,
when I was a bachelor I spent two years in the Masjid(مسجد) not because he was poor,
his father Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه was quite well off.
So he would spend time in the Masjid(مسجد) to be close to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said to the Sahabah(صحابه) in that particular night,
if you have food for two take a third person with you
if you had food for three, take a fourth person
if you had food for four, take a fifth person.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to provide food for Ahlus-Suffah(أهل الصفة) that night
and Rasool Allah ﷺ told the Sahabah(صحابه), the food for two is enough for three
and the food of three is enough for four
and the food the four is enough for five, if Allah puts Barakah(بركة) in it.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, he took three, took them to his house
and entrusted them to Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) his son, but then Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) left
and he went to join Rasool Allah ﷺ, and he had dinner with Rasool Ullah.
An- Nawawi(ألنووي) comments on this and says
that this shows that Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
would put the importance of spending his time with Rasool Allah ﷺ
above his family, above his children, above his guests, and above everything.
So he took the guest to his house and then he went
rather than having dinner with his guests, he went to have it with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Because Rasool Ullah took 10 with him, he took 10 from among Ahlus-Suffah(أهل الصفة)
and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) took three.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه told his family to feed them
and Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) was there at home.
He ended up spending a lot of time with Rasool Allah ﷺ and he came back home, very late.
The wife of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: How come you were late and you didn't feed your guests?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said: You didn't feed them yet!
She said: No! They refused.
Abdur Rahman Bin Abi Bakr(عبدالرحمن إبن أبي بكر), he said:
When I heard that, I ran away to hide
because I know that my father would be very upset.
Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) was not a child at that time he was, he was very old, he's already fought in battles,
but he still was afraid of his father.
So he said: I went in hiding, and my father called me Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن)
the first time, I didn't respond, second time Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن), didn't respond
third time he said: Ya Ghanfar(يا غنفر), Ghanfar(غنفر) is a small fly, blue fly
Ya Ghanfar(يا غنفر)! I knew that he is serious, I responded!
He said: Why didn't you feed them?
So I took my father to them and I said;
Didn't I tell you to eat and you refused and that was true
Abdur Rahman Ibn Abi Bakr(عبدالرحمن إبن أبي بكر) insisted on them to eat
but they said: We are not going to eat this, they said: In the Name of Allah
we're not going to eat until Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) comes back.
He said: Go ahead and eat this.
They said: No! We won't, we're gonna wait for him.
So he told his father, listen! I tried, but they are the ones, who refused.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said: Why didn't you eat?
And he was upset with the guests
I mean, why did you have to wait for all of this time.
And nobody told me and I brought you here to host you.
Why did you end up spending all these hours waiting for me?
So I'm not going to eat you go ahead and eat, they said;
In the name of Allah, we're not going to eat until you eat with us.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said, that's from Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ), and he sat down
what he meant by that is from Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ),
the oath that he made that he's not going to eat with them
and when he saw that they insisted on him eating
and they made an oath in the name of Allah, that he should eat.
He broke his oath, and that is a known in Islam that
if you make an oath in something and then something better comes in terms of goodness
then you do, what is good you make Takfeer(تكفير),
you pay for the oath that you made.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه sat with them to eat.
He said;
Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) is saying is the one who's narrating this Hadith(حديث)
it's in Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم).
He said: Whenever we would take a mouthful, more food would appear.
We keep on taking food more food appears, We eat more food, He said:
The food was growing in the pot, they all were full.
I took the plate back to my wife and said: Look at it.
And she was amazed to see that the plate came with more food on it
than when she sent it.
And then Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه took it to the house of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and some of the other Ahlus-Suffah(أهل الصفة) ate from it
and again it was increasing.
It was a Karmah(كرامة) that happened to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
It is one of the Karamaat(كرامات) of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
A Mo'ijiza(معجزة) happens to Nabi(نَبِي) a Karmah(كرامة) happens to a Wali(ولي)
you have the Mo'jizaat(معجزات)
and these only happened to Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
and then the Karamaat(كرامات) happened to the friends of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So this was a Karmah(كرامة) that occurred to Sayidina(سيدنا) Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was very generous
and his generosity was very well known, and he would be the one
who would always take care of the bill, whenever he's with Rasool Allah ﷺ
he is the one, who would pay.
when Rasool Allah ﷺ was in the early days of Da'wah(دعوة) in Makkah
Abu Dhar Al-Ghaffari رضي الله عنه came into Makkah to inquire about Muhammadﷺ.
He heard about this man, who was claiming to be a Nabi(نَبِي)
so he wants to know more about him.
Abu Dhar Al-Ghaffari(أبوذرألغفاري) was searching for the truth.
He came into Makkah but because the Da'wah(دعوة) was secret in Makkah.
And in those days it was against the law to preach, Islam
it was against the law to practice Islam
it was against the law to even meet with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So Abu Dhar Al-Ghaffari(أبوذرألغفاري) ended up spending an entire month in Makkah
and he is unable to get access to Muhammadﷺ.
Later on, he ended up meeting Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
Rasool Ullah asked him how did you survive for an entire month.
He said: I survived on nothing but the water of Zam-Zam(زمزم)
حتى تكثرت أكن بتني
Until the flesh on my stomach was folding.
You know, with the Bedouins, they were very fit, flat tummies, no fat.
Abu Dhar Al-Ghaffari(أبوذرألغفاري) said:
Not only was the Water of sons Zam-Zam(زمزم) satisfactory for me
but I ended up gaining weight, flesh started to fold on my stomach now.
Now, flesh folding on stomach is usual for everyone today
I mean, it's not a big deal. Everyone has their skin folding on the stomach
but those days it was an achievement that flesh was folding on your stomach
you gained a lot of weight, they were very fit.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
إنها طعامٌ يطعم
Yes it is food, if you wanted it to be so, and in another narration.
,وَشِفاعُ ثمر
And it's healing, if you want it to be so, depending on your Niyyah(نية).
If you drink it for Dua(دُعَا), Allah will fulfill your Dua(دُعَا)
if you drink it as medicine, it's medicine, if you drink it as food, it's food.
As long as you have the intention of a Mo'min(مؤمن), a believer.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abu Bakr(ابوبكر): Go and feed him!
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه took him to his house
and gave him some raisins from At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف), a special treat.
So it was Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) who would always be on the side of Rasool Allah ﷺ, to take care of these expenses.
It was a friendship of sacrifice.
one day in a battle, the Muslims were going on a Ghazwa(غزوة).
Ayesha رضي الله عنها, she lost her necklace.
So she went around looking for her necklace
and it was time for the army to leave.
As she couldn't find her necklace looking around, right, left, she couldn't find out.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ is waiting for her patiently
and his young wife is going around trying to find her necklace she couldn't find it.
But it was getting very late, nightfall
and the people ended up staying there.
Now everybody knew the reason why Rasool Allah ﷺ ended up camping in that place.
They knew it was because Ayesha رضي الله عنها has lost her necklace.
So they went to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and said: Look at what your daughter has done to us
she made us spend the night in a place where there's no water and we have no water.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, he went to Ayesha(عائشه).
So Ayesha(عائشه) says: I was sitting and Rasool Allah ﷺ was sleeping
and his head was on my thigh.
And Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was saying:
This is what you did to us, and he said he was poking me in my waist.
He was very upset and poking me in my waist and saying:
You made us stay in a place where there's no water and we have no water with us.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها says the only reason I wasn't moving
is because Rasool Allah ﷺ was sleeping on my lap
and my father was poking me in my waist.
She said: We ended up spending the night there.
Next day in the morning we had to leave, I didn't find my necklace, nothing to do so.
She said: I went on my camel and as soon as my camel stood up the necklace was under it.
Now, the people who went to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to complain that it was because of Ayesha(عائشه).
But look at what happened,
because they went to sleep in a place, where there's no water and they had no water with them
and they had to wake up in the morning
and make Wudhoo(وضؤ) and some had to make Ghussl(غسل).
That is when the revelation of Tayammum(تيمم) came down.
That was when the revelation of Tayammum(تيمم) came down.
So the Sahabah(صحابه), came back to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه and said;
This is the Barakah(بركة) of your household.
This Ayah(آية) of Tayammum(تيمم) came down, because your daughter lost her necklace,
it is from the Barakaat(بركات) of the household of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
its a blessing.
One can notice here how Rasool Allah ﷺ would treat his family.
With his wives and servants, and children
Rasool Allah ﷺ was very very accommodating
and Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه says:
I have served Rasool Allah ﷺ for my entire life
I never remember a day when he beat me or chastised me
or reprimands me for anything, for my entire life.
Because he was a servant of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ came to Madina
the mother of Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said:
I want to be of his assistance to you.
So here is my son, take him as a servant.
Allah Ho Akbar(الله أكبر), she came and gave up her son to Rasool Allah ﷺ to serve him.
And that was the best thing she did for her son.
For Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك) to be brought up in the household of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and absorb all of that knowledge and to become one of the narrators of the Ahadith(احاديث)
the greatest narratives of the Ahadith(احاديث) among the top seven.
It was because of this decision of his mother, to send them into that line of work
which was service of Rasool Allah ﷺ to be his servant.
Mothers and fathers need to influence their children in the right way.
She could have sent her son to be a great businessman or to be a great farmer
but she made a very good decision, very wise decision.
She chose what was more pleasing to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and it paid back, immensely.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has blessed her son, Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه
one of the greatest of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار).
So, don't be so concerned about the Rizq(رزق) of your children
because it's not you who's giving them Rizq(رزق), it's Allah, who is giving them rizq(رزق).
In fact you're benefiting from that rizq(رزق)
because whenever you have a child who was born
the Rizq(رزق) comes with them and you end up consuming some of that
because you're the one who's raising them up.
Every child comes with their own Rizq(رزق).
You did not provide for yourself, how could you provide for your children?
You are not the one, who's making your Rizq(رزق) is coming to you from Allah.
So if you can't do it for yourself how can you do it for your children
therefore care for what's most important, that you save them from Hellfire.
قُوا أَنْفُسَكُمْ وَأَهْلِيكُمْ نَارًا وَقُودُهَا النَّاسُ وَالْحِجَارَةُ
Save yourselves and your families from hellfire.
That's the responsibility of the head of the household
save yourself and your family from Jahannum(جهنم).
When Hadift-Al-Ifq(حادفة ألعفق) happened.
When the rumor was going around about Ayesha رضي الله عنها and they accused her.
One of the poor relatives of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
who was sponsored financially by Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) got involved in this rumor.
I mean, he spoke against Ayesha رضي الله عنها.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was upset
he's talking about my daughter, negatively.
So he said: I'm not gonna spend any money on him, anymore.
See Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would take care of the entire expenses of some families
and the family of Mustakh(مسطح), was one of them
but because he got involved in this rumor against Ayesha رضي الله عنها
he said: I'm not gonna support him anymore.
The following Ayah(آية) was revealed, talking about Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
and other people who are in the same situation as Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
وَلَا يَأْتَلِ أُولُو الْفَضْلِ مِنكُمْ وَالسَّعَةِ أَن يُؤْتُوا أُولِي الْقُرْبَىٰ وَالْمَسَاكِينَ وَالْمُهَاجِرِينَ فِي سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ ۖ
وَلْيَعْفُوا وَلْيَصْفَحُوا ۗ أَلَا تُحِبُّونَ أَن يَغْفِرَ اللَّهُ لَكُمْ ۗ وَاللَّهُ غَفُورٌ رَّحِيمٌ۝
And let not those of virtue among you, and wealth, swear not to give aid to their relatives
and the needy and the immigrants for the cause of Allah
and let them pardon and overlook.
Would you not like that Allah should forgive you.
And Allah is Forgiving and Merciful.
So Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: And let not those among you of virtue.
So, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is saying that Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is a man of virtue
Allah is saying: Don't stop spending on them, don't you want Allah to forgive you.
As soon as Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) heard the Ayah(آية), he said: Yes! I want Allah to forgive me.
And from then on, he started taking care of Mustakh(مسطح) again.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه continued making doing business
when he was in Madina, he traveled to Syria, Ash-Sham(ألشام)
so he continued doing that to make a living.
Even though he wanted to be close to Rasool Allah ﷺ
but he had to travel to make a living, seeking Rizq(رزق)
he didn't stop, even though he became very busy in his life in Madina.
And with Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه every moment that he would spend in his business, is rewardable
because his money would end up being spent in the sake of Islam.
So really his business was Ibadah(عبادة)
because his wealth was for the service of Rasool Allah ﷺ and the religion.
So it is exactly like he's doing any other Ibadah(عبادة).
We can see that from the narration that I will mention to you now.
That Rasool Allah ﷺ was very grateful to his friendship with Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
Rabia Al-Aslami(ربيعة ألأسلمي), he said that Rasool Allah ﷺ gave me a piece of land
and he gave Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه a piece of land, next to mine.
And then Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) came between me and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and we had a dispute on a palm tree.
I claimed it to be in my land and he claimed it to be in his land.
So we had an argument.
He then said, something to me that made me upset
he said the harsh word that made me upset.
But then he immediately regretted that. And he said;
O Rabiah(ربيعة) reply back to me, so that we can get even.
Look at the nature of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
even though he got upset and he mentioned something harsh to Rabiah(ربيعة)
but he immediately came back and he said: No!
I want you, to respond back to me so that we can be even.
Because Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) doesn't have hard feelings against anyone.
So he told him: Reply back to me.
Rabiah(ربيعة) said: I won't!
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: You would reply back to me
otherwise I'm going to go and complain to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
That's how serious he took it.
Because he doesn't want to face Allah on the Day of Judgment owing anything to anyone.
He wants to be clean, he doesn't want to have in the heart of anyone hard feelings towards him.
So he told them go back.
Come on, and respond back to me otherwise I'm gonna go and complain to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He said: I'm not gonna respond back to you
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه angrily left.
and he was going to Rasool Allah ﷺ, Rabiah(ربيعة) said: I followed him.
But then, some men from my tribe, clan Aslam(أسلم) came to me and said;
Why is he, going to complain about you, when he is the one
who spoke ill about you in the first place?
Why is he going to complain about you?
Rabiah(ربيعة) said: Do you know, who he is?
This is Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, the second of two.
He comes second after Rasool Allah ﷺ
and I don't want him to see you gathering around me
otherwise he's gonna think that we're ganging up against him.
And if he gets upset than Rasool Allah ﷺ will become upset
and if Rasool Allah ﷺ becomes upset, then Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will have His wrath on me
and that will be the end of Rabiah(ربيعة).
Get away from me! Go away!
Rabiah رضي الله عنه knows who Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is.
He didn't want Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to even see these people gathering around him
because he might interpret that they coming to give him support.
And even though Rabiah(ربيعة) knew that it was Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) who spoke ill about him.
He still refused to reply, and he also refused to get the assistance of his family.
He said: Leave me alone!
And then he went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was sitting next to him.
Rabiah(ربيعة) says: Rasool Allah ﷺ was sitting so he looked up at me and said;
يا ربيعة ما لك والصديق
O Rabiah(ربيعة), what's your issue with As-Siddique(ألصديق)?
The Siddique(ألصديق), that was the name Rasool Allah ﷺ would call him, As-Siddique(ألصديق)
What's your issue with Siddique(ألصديق).?
Rabiah(ربيعة) said: O Messenger of Allah, we had this argument
because of such and such.
And he said something to me that upset me.
And then he told me, to answer back and I refused
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
أجل
Yes! Do not respond back to him but say
O Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), May Allah forgive you!
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said: You did the right thing.
You should not respond back to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
even if he commits wrong against you.
Don't reply, don't respond back! Rather, you should say;
May Allah forgive you!
Not only that, not only should you be quiet
but you need to make Dua(دُعَا) that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ forgives Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
That's how much love Rasool Allah ﷺ had to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
and that's how much gratitude, he had towards him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would show extreme loyalty to the ones who were with him from day one.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ later on, when he opened Makkah all of these great politicians,
who everybody at that time would want to be close to and have relationship with like, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان)
and all of the other great men of Arabia at the time in terms of their status and nobility among the people
but Rasool Allah ﷺ would consider the best to be the ones who came with him from day one, even if they were slaves.
Rasool Allah ﷺ still remembered the service that they showed to him and to Islam
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was very grateful for that.
And that's why Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he felt that he was leaving this world
when he felt that he is on the doorstep of death.
He went to the battleground of Uhud(أحَد)
and he spoke to the Shuhadah(شهداء) of Uhud(أحَد), and said;
I am going to be your witness on the Day of Judgment
you gave up your life for the service of this religion.
I am going to witness for you on the Day of Judgment
and Rasool Allah ﷺ when he was passing away. He said:
Close all of the doors of the Masjid(مسجد) except the door of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
keep it open.
One day Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه had an argument with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was sitting with the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم
and here comes Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) running
and the narrator of the Hadith(حديث) said;
He has lifted his Izaar(إزار) so his knee was uncovered.
Rasool Allah ﷺ when he saw Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), and he looked at his face. He said:
أمَّا صاحبكم فقد غامر
Your friend has been involved in a dispute, I can see it, in his face.
When Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه came in and he gave Salam(سلام)
Rasool Allah ﷺ responded and said: What's the problem Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه  said: I had an argument with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
so I spoke ill about him, but then I regretted that.
So I told him: O Umar(عُمَر) forgive me, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
I am not gonna forgive you!
I told Umar(عُمَر), O Umar(عُمَر) forgive me. He refused and he left.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he regreted that.
So he went to the house of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
you can see the Sahabah(صحابه), are very fast in forgiving
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) he went to the house of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and said;
أثمَّ ابوبكر
Is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) there.? They said: No!
So he knew that he is gonna be with Rasool Allah ﷺ
so he went there, and when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was coming
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه saw that the face of Rasool Allah ﷺ changed
ثمعارة وجه
You could tell when Rasool Allah ﷺ is angry and upset
his facial expressions would change.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said;
فأشفكت
I felt sorry for Umar(عُمَر)
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was now worried
that Rasool Allah ﷺ would be upset with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) he went down on his knees and he said;
O Rasool Ullah: I am the one, who transgressed against him
because Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) felt that Rasool Allah ﷺ was angry
and this anger was directed at Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
So he wanted to make it clear that it was his fault in the first place.
He is the one who spoke ill against Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
But even though Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) mentioned that twice
and clarify the situation, Rasool Allah ﷺ his facial expressions were still angry.
And he said: When I came to you, you said that I am a liar
and Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said that you are telling the truth.
And he consoled me with his self, and his wealth
so are you going to keep my friend alone.
Are you going to keep my friend alone and he said it twice.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to make it clear to the Sahabah(صحابه).
Do not harm Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
He's the greatest among you!
Leave them alone and don't harm him.
Because I'm going to stand for his defense
I'm going to be on the side.
The narrator of this Hadith(حديث) said;
We never saw anybody after that daring to cause any harm to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
We left him alone. This was in Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ).
وصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ